Henry Fountain Ashurst papers, 1896-1963 (bulk 1920-1962)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Henry Fountain Ashurst papers, 1896-1963 (bulk 1920-1962)
AZ 002
Ashurst, Henry Fountain, 1874-1962
4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Senator from Arizona; born in Winnemucca, Humboldt County, Nev., September 13, 1874; moved with his parents to Arizona in 1875 and settled near the present town of Flagstaff, Coconino County; attended the public schools of Flagstaff and was graduated from the Stockton (Calif.) Business College in 1896; studied law and political economy at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor; was admitted to the bar in 1897 and commenced practice in Williams, Ariz.
Ashurst was a member of the Territorial house of representatives in 1897 and 1899, serving as speaker in 1899; served in the Territorial senate in 1903; district attorney of Coconino County 1905-1908; moved to Prescott, Ariz., in 1909 and continued the practice of law; upon the admission of Arizona as a State was elected as a Democrat to the United States Senate on March 27, 1912 and served to January 3, 1941.
Senator Ashurst was chairman of the Committee on Indian Affairs (Sixty-third through Sixty-fifth Congresses), Committee on Industrial Expositions (Sixty-third Congress), Committee to Investigate Trespassers on Indian Land (Sixty-sixth Congress), and the Committee on the Judiciary (Seventy-third through Seventy-sixth Congresses). Ashurst was appointed a member of the Board of Immigration Appeals in the Department of Justice on April 8, 1941, and served until February 28, 1943, when he retired. Senator Ashurst died in Washington, D.C., May 31, 1962.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1912-1963
Series II: Speeches, 1906-1962
Series III: Biographical Material, 1896-1962
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, typescripts of speeches, and biographical materials, including clippings, photographs, diary, expense records, cartoons, and reprints relating to his career and studies of his career by George Fray Sparks and others.
Access Terms
Ashurst, Henry Fountain, 1874-1962 -- Archives; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909- -- Correspondence; Sparks, George Fray, 1912-1983; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944; Legislators -- United States; Speeches, addresses, etc., American -- 20th century -- Arizona; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; Arizona -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs; Diaries
Related Material
Geroge Sparks's thesis on Ashurst is located under call number: AZ 123.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1912-1962
  - Correspondence. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1912-September 23, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - Correspondence. September 24, 1940-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Correspondence. 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Barry Goldwater letters regarding Ashurst's speech to the Arizona Bar Association. 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1958-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence: George Sparks and H.F.A. 1950-1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: George Sparks and others regarding his various Ashurst studies. 1951-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series II: Speeches, 1906-1962
  - Speeches (most representative and important). 1906-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - H.F.A. in the Congressional Record (bound volume). 1913-1914 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - H.F.A. in the Congressional Record. 1916-1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reprints of speeches. 1909-1929 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Reprints of speeches. 1932-1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Speeches (typescripts). 1915-1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Speeches (typescripts). No Date (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous notes for speeches. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Franked mail to constituents (examples). (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series III: Biographical Material, 1896-1963
  - Personal and biographical papers--miscellaneous. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Clippings. 1896-1963 (Box 5, Folder 2-6)
  - Photographs (family). 1920s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photographs. 1930-1962 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Diary (typescript, carbon). June 1910-July 1937 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - "Up in Coconino County," (extract from H.F.A.'s journal). May 10, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Biographical sketches. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Certificates of election. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Washington social life: Evalyn Walsh McLean (clippings, invitations). (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Washington social life: Perle Mesta and others (clippings, invitations). (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Expense records. 1922, 1928, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Expense records. 1940 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - George Sparks: miscellaneous material regarding his dissertation, "The Speaking of Henry Fountain Ashurst." (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - George Sparks: miscellaneous studies regarding H.F.A. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Words (clippings, notes). (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Poems and Parodies (by various persons, including H.F.A.). (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bible material (notes, clippings, typescripts of addresses). (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Shakespeare material (notes, clippings, fragments of addresses). (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Inauguration of M.L. Quezon, first President of the Philippines and related material. 1935 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, containing addresses, necrology lists, vocabulary lists, quotations, notes on theatres and plays, some personal thoughts. (Box 7)
  - William Blackstone's Commentaties on the Laws of England, 3rd ed. Chicago, 1884, 2 volumes. (Box 7)
  - Speeches of Henry Fountain Ashurst of Arizona. Published by Senator Barry Goldwater, copy inscribed to George F. Sparks by H.F.A. 1953 (Box 7)
  - Envelope containing photographs of U.S. Senators, about the turn of the century. (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes (empty) addressed in H.F.A.'s hand. (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of clippings. 1916-1962 (Box 8)
  - Cartoons (8 original cartoons of H.F.A.; folder of newspaper reporductions). (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous oversize items (photographs, certificates and awards, etc.). (Box 10)